welcome to meditating with John Breaux
Vicki I'm a cognitive psychologist in
the cognitive scientists at the
University of Toronto where I
academically teach in scientific study
in research phenomena like mindfulness
related phenomena such as Insight flow
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
and the aspiration to enlightenment I've
been practicing the pasta meditation
that a contemplation Tai Chi Chuan and
Qigong for over 29 years and teaching
them professionally for close to 20
years welcome if you're joining us for
the first time you should know that this
is a course in fact the introductory
course is done what you can do is you
can go into the lake the notes for this
video and find links to previous lessons
I recommend doing a new lesson like
every Saturday or Sunday and that way
you can slowly catch up as you continue
to participate in this Sangha every
other Monday is the Dharma day in which
I teach principles and practices more
advanced principles and practices that
build on the previous principles and
practices every day we said from 9:30 to
10:00 at the end of every day there is a
QA please keep your Q&A s got time to
questions concerning this ecology
practices this course if you have more
encompassing questions please come to
the live stream on YouTube
monthly Q&A every third Friday of the
month that will be June 19th of this
month and it's at 3 p.m. Eastern Time
please like this video stream to raise
its visibility in the YouTube algorithm
so I can help as many people as possible
with this course I think that's
everything we need to do with respect to
announcements this upcoming Monday will
be a derma day and I'm going to start
teaching you
a bit of it practices drawn more from
the Taoist tradition so much more embody
practices to help supplement and develop
but we're already doing want to build a
rich vibrant dynamic ecology of
practices all right so look at yourself
in your basic posture set your phones on
do not disturb and we will begin when I
say baguette begin
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate and you cultivated any
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay so we have some time for some
questions a question for Manuel post
I've been having issues labeling fonts
and Counting the act of making myself
conscious verbally of the action is
taking too much my focus so I'm not
quite sure what you mean by too much of
your focus do you mean that the act of
speaking is sort of taking out of that
meditative focus that you're in perhaps
that's what you mean if you can step
back and note your distractions as a
process if you can step back and note
them from the from the standpoint of the
five factors of inquiring mindfulness
and if you can do all of that without in
their speech and let go of the inner
speech the inner speech is a coach that
eventually you let go of you don't need
it anymore
so if you can do all of what we've been
training without having to do the actual
inner verbalization because you find
that perhaps jarring you out of the
mindfulness state then don't do it
but if what's happening is right your
your what you're saying is well when I
label it sort of brings me sort of it's
a demand on me
so the hesitancy there I have if that's
if there's another thing you might be
talking about which is you sort of
getting into a lulled State that's I
don't know if this is the case you're
getting into a very low state and the
act of sort of labeling and destruction
wakes you up a bit alerts that is
something that you should try and step
away from and you should then embrace
the act of the labeling because it's
actually bringing the alertness to your
mind so I suspect it's probably the
first that I mentioned
that you're you're getting to a place
where verbalization is actually
disruptive of the mindfulness that you
can bring to bear enquiring mind fulness
you can bring to bear on your
distractions and if that's the case let
the verbalization go it is just a raft
it is just a coach but as I said if
what's happening is you're getting into
a very low dulled state and it's feeling
sort of warm and fuzzy and cozy and you
don't like to do the verbal distraction
the verbal labeling of your distractions
because it's sort of waking you up and
jarring you then you should be doing the
labeling so whichever one of those it's
most appropriate in the one give up the
verbalization and the other you may need
to embrace it more as I said I suspect
for you it's probably the former mark
without high mark what do I do if I can
hear and feel my heart beating other
special ways to deal with this
conditions not particularly quickly just
hyper aware okay so this is going to
happen to many people along this journey
and it's going to happen
it's also different parts of your body
at different stages so as we practice
insula especially sorry as we practice
there are introspective behaviors like
becoming more aware of our body we're
activating the insula this is a part of
our brain part and that the insula is
always not also active when we're
picking up on other people's mental
states so it's very powerfully engaged
in mindfulness dan Siegel argues and I
think he's correct that what we're doing
with mindfulness is we're taking the
ability we use picking up on other
people's mental states and we're
internalizing it we're turning out
turning it on ourselves so what's gonna
happen as we do this practice is we're
going that this is why people also get
synesthetic some people when they're
practicing your your insula is going to
significantly increase so for example
one of the measures we we make of how
well people can pick up pick up on other
people's mental states and and therefore
how much they might be and and the lack
thereof is pretty good is predictive of
them being psychopathic
as we do the pulse test sit sit here and
without touching yourself like I mean
touching your pulse count your heart
beats the nest next time seconds better
you are at that the more accurate you
are at that is how its predictive of how
well you can pick up on other people's
mental states how sensitive also you'll
be coming to your own mental states so
you're going to get these along the way
you're going to get these will seem like
hyper sensitization hyper enhancement of
interoceptive awareness you'll also get
the reverse who get suddenly be other
people's emotions will suddenly be more
present to you and that can also also be
unpleasant so the thing to do is first
of all to note that this isn't I mean
I'm not a doctor and as long as you know
there's nothing else pathological going
on I mean physiologically pathological
right so I take that into consideration
probably not the case but right but
frame this as this is a normal part of
the path also in a sense welcome it
because it's like it's like you've been
blind I mean and now you can see and
it's going to be startling and
distracting it's going to be super
salient to you but if you normalize if
you incorporate it what will happen is
it will start to background you can't
make it background imagine if you didn't
house I can and I gave you color vision
you couldn't sort of I won't see you
have to let it normalize itself you have
to you have to let it be incorporated
and internalized into your new way of
being this is a way in which we grow our
Buddha so try to frame it as a welcoming
sign of an emerging sensitivity and
emerging Sensibility
do you practice and let it naturalize
itself for you Kiriko ger good to hear
from you again Kara does the ecology
practices that you'll be teaching and if
you include any kind of forgiveness
practice typically I don't have a
forgiveness practice for people because
this is a difficult one for me because
I've thought a lot about this so I see
and I understand what people would
disagree with me on this but I see the
way I'm trying to teach Metta as
reciprocal opening as forgiving so what
I mean by that is when I do proper meta
I give right a gift before I four give
the possibility the real active engaged
power for a new identity for you and me
and for us in our relationship and I
take that to be what Jesus of Nazareth
originally met by forgiving to give
before two four years fo re2 for you and
therefore I think meta is in that deep
sense of forgiving properties you
probably mean the more standard
especially post Protestant notion
Christian ocean of forgiveness and I
don't specifically have any practices
like that
for the reason that in our particular
cultural context that and what I'm
trying to teach with meta get confused
and they undermine each other in that
confusion in that equivocation
especially for people who are starting
out a lot of these practices however if
you can keep them apart and set them
into proper relationship with each other
there are forgiving practices you can go
into the Christian meditation tradition
especially the centering prayers and the
prayer of the heart and then they have a
ten
supplementary forgiving practices and
you may be able to integrate that with
what I'm teaching you I hope that was
hopeful the your taro Nakamura I found
meditation called body scan what do you
think about it the body scan is derived
from Jon kabat-zinn z-- MBSR a
mindfulness based stress reduction and
when I'm teaching you to find your flow
that's basically the same thing during
the body's yet
I tend to emphasize the cultivation of
flow and not just the scanning awareness
and so it integrates aspect of the body
scan with the task of all actually
helping to cultivate the flow state and
thereby enhance absorption so I think
the two are deeply integrated in in what
I'm teaching you this is really good
questions you know I mean you teach the
best when you're learning right and I
want to think of it with these questions
they make me reflect they help me to
explicate they deduce they draw out from
me so thank you very much and I want to
always be responsive and responsible to
them it's really important to me so I
think we're taking a look to see if
there's any more questions amar is
behind the scenes seeing if there's any
more so I'm going to just wait for a
second and see if there's any more
looks like we're we're done for today
that's great remember that Monday will
be a Dharma day I want to thank
everybody for joining as I've said the
saying that this is my Sangha too and I
really appreciate it
so thanks to my dear friend and
technomage amar who is always behind the
scenes making so many things happen
thank you to my beloved son Jason who's
always here pinch-hitting is needed
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified at the next video
my channel you'll find the lecture
series awakening from the meeting
process voices with Roubaix keys which
is a discussion series and you'll find
all of this and much more developed in
depth more comprehensively and more
integrated in fashion and by the others
please who might benefit from this
series to join theirs
all of the resources are there for them
to catch up at their own pace so please
help me to help as many people as
possible
Brett is here pleasured out discord
server just fantastic I know gosh 10
stock was on recently talking about
circling at depth was just amazing and I
know that there's a group of people that
meet right on the discourse River
joining the Sangha they talk about the
practice they do some lectio divina
there's the community there it's vibrant
and vital please please if you can
partake of it participate in it it will
nourish you there's a link to that
discourse River in the description for
this video please remember that we're
doing this every weekday morning 9:30
Eastern Time
please also remember that continuity of
practice is more important than quantity
of practice there's no enemy worse than
your own mind and body
there is no friend no ally no true
companion on the way better than your
own mind and body be laughs unto
yourself I'll see you on Monday for
Dharma day take a care of me one